Finding Aid for Frank Michael Landers papers, 1935-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank Michael Landers papers 1935-1990, 1945-1975
Landers, Frank Michael, 1911-
3 linear feet
9789 Aa 2
Career civil servant from Michigan who worked in state government revenue and budgeting agencies, and in the federal government as a budget consultant to foreign governments; the series in the collection are titled: Foreign Service, Fiscal Management, Writings on Government, and Photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Betty Landers (donor no. 8631 ) in July 1997.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Frank M. Landers was a career civil servant who worked in the Michigan state government and in the federal government. Landers was born in Holyoke, Massachusetts in 1911. He attended the University of Michigan as an undergraduate, and also did graduate work in public administration at the University. After receiving his Masters degree in public administration in 1936, Landers began working as a researcher for the Michigan State Welfare and Relief Study Commission. The next year, he was appointed Chief of the County Finance Unit of the State Emergency Relief Agency. In 1938, Landers took a job with the State Tax Commission, but left within a year to research and teach at the University of Michigan's Bureau of Government. He returned to the State Tax Commission in 1941, as the Secretary. In 1942-43, Landers left state government to work for the United States Bureau of the Budget. In 1943, he left the Bureau for military service in the Naval Reserve. With the end of the war, Landers returned to work for the Michigan state government as the research director of the Department of Revenue. In 1949, he was appointed director of the budget in the Department of Administration, where he remained until 1961. During his tenure as the director of the budget, he twice served as a budget consultant for foreign governments: in the Philippines in 1954 and in Vietnam in 1956.
In 1961, Landers again left state government and began working for the United States Operations Mission (USOM), a U. S. State Department agency promoting Third World development. Landers worked for the agency in the Philippines in 1961-1962 and in Korea from 1962 to 1967. In 1968 he began working for the Agency for International Development (AID) in Vietnam, and then worked for AID in Pakistan from 1969 to 1974. He retired in 1975, but continued to write and research. In addition to his work for the government, Landers was involved in the National Association of State Budget Officers (NASBO), serving as president in 1954-55.
The Frank M. Landers papers document his experience as a state and federal government official and consultant to foreign governments. The papers are arranged in four series: Foreign Service, Fiscal Management, Writings on Government, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Landers, Frank Michael.; Budget--Michigan.; Diplomatic and consular service, American.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Korea.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Pakistan.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Philippines.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Vietnam.; Finance, Public--Michigan.; Michigan--Appropriations and expenditures.; Korea.; Pakistan.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; Vietnam.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Landers, Frank Michael.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Foreign Service
  The Foreign Service series consists of material relating to Landers' work in the Philippines, Vietnam, Korea and Pakistan. The series includes reports, notes, and correspondence. The material in this series gives some insight into the activities of American Third World development agencies in the 1960s and 1970s.
  - 1954 Philippines (Box 1)
  - 1956 Vietnam, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 Philippines, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1962-1967 Korea
    - Speeches and Articles 1962-1967 (Box 1)
    - Korean Government Organization 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - USOM Reports circa 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Technical Assistance in Public Administration"; USOM Korea Report by Landers 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1973 Pakistan
    - Background Material and Notes 1965-1970 (Box 1)
    - Reports and Memos 1970-1973, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Notes 1970-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Notes and Reports 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Appointment Calendar 1971 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Reform; Correspondence and Reports 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Reports of the Management Goals Committee, USAID 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Notes, Correspondence, Speeches 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - General Material on Asian Development
    - "U.S. Technical Assistance in Public Administration in East Asia," by Landers 1968 (Box 1)
    - AID Material 1967-1974 (Box 1)
    - AID Material on Vietnam and Korea 1967-1969 (Box 2)
    - Papers and Reports on Asian Development 1967-1968 (Box 2)
- Fiscal Management
  The Fiscal Management series consists of material from the State Tax Commission, correspondence and reports about the planning of the Michigan state budget, secondary material about the practice of fiscal management, and Landers' correspondence and notes relating to the National Association of State Budget Officers (NASBO). The series mostly consists of reports and correspondence.
  - State Tax Commission Material 1938, 3 binders (Box 2)
  - "An Analysis of the Problems Involved in Allocation of State Relief Funds," by Landers 1938 (Box 2)
  - State Budget Material
    - State Budget 1939-1960, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Report on Budget by Landers 1959 (Box 2)
    - Budget Preparation 1960 (Box 2)
    - Revenue Estimation 1947-1961 (Box 2)
    - Budget Division 1947-1949 (Box 2)
    - Department of Administration 1948-1960, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Department of Administration; Conflict with Auditor General 1956 (Box 2)
  - Writings and Speeches on the Practice of Fiscal Management
    - "Local Budgets and State Assistance," Reports 1947 (Box 2)
    - Federal Aid and State Budgets; Articles 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - "Towards a Simplification of the Federal Budget," 1973 (Box 2)
    - Articles, Speeches and Papers on Budgeting 1935-1955, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Articles, Speeches and Papers on budgeting 1954-1968, undated, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - "Property Tax in Michigan," Undated Manuscript (Box 3)
    - Notes on Property Tax 1990 (Box 3)
  - National Association of State Budget Officers
    - Correspondence 1954-1958, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Reports 1958-1961 (Box 3)
- Writings on Government
  The Writings on Government series consists of reports, articles and a book that Landers wrote on the subject of government. The book A Bureaucratic View of the Michigan State Government, is a study of the functioning of the state bureaucracy and also serves as a memoir of Landers' years in the state government.
  - "Michigan Seeks Better Management," 1948 (Box 3)
  - "State Administrative Reform in Michigan," 1954 (Box 3)
  - Articles on Government circa 1974 (Box 3)
  - "Local Government in Branch County," 1975 (Box 3)
  - "Michigan's Lawmakers," 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - A Bureaucratic View of Michigan State Government, 1935-1960, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re A Bureaucratic View, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - List of Landers' Speeches and Articles 1938-1982 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of one folder of photos from Landers foreign service and state government career, and a binder of photographs from the Budget Division of the Board of Administration.
  - Photographs circa 1954-1985 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Division of Budget Photo Album circa 1957-1961 (Box 3)